Let me show you something. In March
2026, a photo went viral on Reddit of
two United States Immigration and
Customs Enforcement agents patrolling
the corridors of New York's LaGuardia
Airport.
All things considered, it wasn't a
particularly notable picture. If ICE is
going to be anywhere, makes a whole lot
more sense for them to be at an airport
than at the Super Bowl. There was one
thing which stuck out, though.
The agents seemed really, really young.
[music]
With their cool, young people haircuts,
they looked like they were part of some
kind of reverse 21 Jump Street program.
And Reddit users began to mock them
relentlessly. As far as I can tell, no
journalist ever quite managed to confirm
how old the agents actually were. But
the presence of younger-than-usual
recruits would certainly have made
sense. The previous August, then
Secretary of Homeland Security Kirstjen
Nielsen had lowered the age limit for
joining ICE from 21 to 18. This was amid
a huge recruitment drive for the agency.
Join ICE and [music] help us catch the
worst of the worst. Drug traffickers,
gang members, predators. [music]
With ICE being sent to effectively
occupy the Twin Cities of Minneapolis
and St. Paul in an effort to round up
allegedly legal immigrants, Noem and
Trump needed as many bodies as they
could muster. They didn't only drop the
age limit. Noem also announced a $50,000
sign-on bonus and a student forgiveness
program worth a further $60,000. The
eligibility criteria: an ability to
complete 15 push-ups, 32 sit-ups, and
run 1.5 miles in a leisurely 14 minutes.
[music] The Atlanta Black Star
summarized the recruitment criteria in
four simple words: anything with a
pulse.
It worked. Soon, the Department of
Homeland Security was celebrating a 120%
increase in the number of agents on its
books. And yet, the consequences of
these lax standards were just what you'd
expect.
>> [music]
>> Things got far worse than just some
agents looking a little on the young
side. The footage which emerged from
Minneapolis during ISIS' so-called
Operation Metro Surge was terrifying,
but also kind of farcical. Agents
appeared out of shape. They were
undisciplined. They also just looked
hopelessly out of their depth. When two
citizens, Alex Wint and Renée Good, were
killed in separate incidents, their
murders seemed as much the result of a
cascade of incompetence across many
different levels [clears throat] as
anything else. None of this is how we
imagine these things working when it
comes to far-right governments. [music]
When we picture a dystopian society in
which an aspiring dictator assembles
their own private army, we tend to
picture a well-oiled military machine,
something like the Peacekeepers from The
Hunger Games or the First Order from the
Star Wars sequel trilogy. The end of a
regime that acquiesces to dispoil. What
we got instead was the Stormtroopers
from the Star Wars original trilogy.
Take over.
Need a hand? As much as liberals often
like to think of Trump as an evil force,
he's just as often been a hapless one.
Are you still a believer in Santa? Cuz
at 7:00 it's my general, right?
Particularly in his second presidency,
his track record has been one of failure
after failure [music] after failure. The
more chaos and increased cost of living
which has followed from Trump's chaotic
second reign, the lower his approval
ratings have sunk. As the conservative
writers Peter Wehner and Robert P.
Beschel Jr. had predicted the previous
August, Trump's casual supporters didn't
mind the cruelty.
>> [music]
>> They could overlook a little sexual
assault, corruption, or insurrection.
The one thing they haven't been able to
forgive [music]
is incompetence.
And that same incompetence could be
about to take the wind out of the sails
of ascendant far-right parties across
the world.
Good evening, Birmingham!
Let me shift focus to the UK. [music]
This week, a good proportion of the
adult population of Great Britain will
heading to the polls in a series of
local elections. Maybe they've happened
by the time you're watching this, maybe
they haven't. It doesn't really matter
because the broad narrative of the
results is pretty certain. Nigel Farage,
leader of the far-right Reform UK party,
is set to have an incredible night. His
party has a strong chance of winning the
Welsh Senate and of taking control of
county and city councils across England,
even including some in London. Other
small parties are likely to benefit,
too. The Green Party, in particular, is
on track to make some really big gains.
Nevertheless, the few hundred seats that
the Greens are set to gain pale in
comparison to the more than 1,000 new
councilors which Nigel Farage is hoping
to walk away with. Britain is about to
get very reformy. Or, you know, maybe
the Monster Raving Loony Party will
completely sweep the board. Such is the
danger of me filming this more than a
week in advance. There's a morbid sense
of inevitability to these election
results. It feels like the UK, like many
other countries in Europe and elsewhere,
is on this inevitable trudge to the
right. Wins in local elections for the
Reform Party this year and the next and
the next are but an aperitif for an
inevitable seizure of the full power of
the state at the next general election
in 2029. Prime Minister Nigel Farage
will then be able to go and join
President Vance, Prime Minister Meloni,
President Le Pen, and Chancellor Vidal
as they plan a new far-right world order
at G7 meetings which will presumably all
be held in the headquarters of the
Springfield Republican Party.
But, what if it's not that simple? What
if these various Trump hangers-on, all
of whom have at one point or another
seen both Trump and Maga as templates
for their own careers, might similarly
[music] be stymied by very Trumpian
run-ins with incompetence.
Yeah, yeah.
>> Paul! Paul, I'm going to mute you in a
minute. You're just going to have to
suck it up, okay? This is a
recording of a Zoom call between members
[clears throat] of the Reform UK group
on Kent County Council.
It was October 2025, and Reform had
recently won control of the council
during the local elections which took
place during the May of that year. Their
victory in Kent, as well as 11 other
areas of England, was a big moment for
Reform, their biggest yet. The party had
managed to get several members of
Parliament elected before. They'd also
persuaded several MPs from other parties
to join theirs, even if they lost one MP
to his own new party as a result of not
being racist enough. As members of what
is, in Parliament at least, an
absolutely minuscule political party,
however, Reform's MPs don't really have
anything in the way of responsibility.
Their job is to sit at the back of the
opposition benches and throw verbal
tomatoes at the Prime Minister and his
cabinet. All of which is kind of easy.
[music]
One doesn't have to be a massive Keir
Starmer super fan to recognize that it
is far easier to sit back and criticize
the way the government is doing stuff
than to actually have to make a go of
things yourself. May 2025, then,
anointed Reform UK with something it
never really had before.
Responsibility.
The party itself saw its new-found power
as the ruling party in county councils
like Kent as an incredible opportunity
to prove [music] their worth. Nigel
Farage was said to have described such
councils as a shop window into what a
Reform government in Westminster would
be capable of should they win the next
general election. Unfortunately for
Nigel, what they were capable of was
making an absolute out of
everything they touched. One of the
party's earliest challenges came in
trying to hang on to all of those
councilors that they'd managed to get
elected, many of whom appeared as if
they hadn't really expected to win.
Perhaps the highest profile example of
this was Rob Howard, the extremely
short-lived leader of Warwickshire
County Council, who a Google search
tells me didn't direct the 2006
adaptation of The Da Vinci Code starring
Tom Hanks. Interpret for me, please,
this symbol. First thing that comes to
mind, anybody. Hatred. Racism. Howard
was elected leader of the council by his
fellow councillors on the 16th of May.
Then, just 41 days later, he resigned,
citing health problems which he said
limited his ability [music] to do the
job to the standard required. Although
he has continued to serve as both a
councillor and as member of the
council's cabinet since. On standing
down, Howard was replaced by his deputy,
George Finch, who happened to be the
grand old age of 18. Barely out of
school, Finch found himself in charge of
a council which controls around 1.5
billion pounds in assets and which has
an annual budget of half a billion
pounds. I don't just watch Nelson
Mandela films in [music] November. It's
like history month.
I I'll watch them whenever cuz he's
inspirational. It hasn't just been
Warwickshire, though. In the less than 1
year since Reform's big victorious night
at the polls, the party has lost around
70 councillors, either through them
quitting the party, the party giving
them the boot, or them quitting as
councillors altogether. Some have been
kicked out of Reform as a result of
inter-clique fallings-out within local
parties. Following the leak of that
chaotic [music] Zoom calling Kent, for
example, the local party suspended and
then expelled four of the councillors
present [music] for bringing the party
into disrepute. Crucially not Lyndon Kem
Carren, the one filmed shouting at
everyone, but four of the people she
reckoned might have leaked the
recording. Sometimes I will make a
decision
that might not be liked by everybody in
the group.
But I'm afraid
you're just going to have to So,
it up, okay? Others have been suspended
for the thing that you would expect
members of a far-right political party
to be suspended for. Sound the boomers
making horrific social media posts on
accounts which use their full government
names alarm. There was Ian Cooper,
one-time leader of Staffordshire County
Council, who was expelled after being
accused of sending [music] racist abuse
to Sadiq Khan and David Lammy. There was
Lancashire's Tom Pickup, who was found
to have described Keir Starmer as a
dictator in a WhatsApp group in which
other members have called for a mass
Islam genocide. There was Laura Ann
Jones from Wales, who also got caught
out on WhatsApp after dropping a slur
for Chinese people whilst discussing
TikTok. Not to forget Northumberland
Councillor John Allen, who was expelled
from the party after it was alleged that
he had a YouTube account with which he'd
left comments under videos promising to
shoot Keir Starmer, which is unfair
because personally I think anyone who
comments on YouTube videos at all should
go straight to jail. Some of Reform's
councillors were wrong 'uns in real
life, too. Corby Councillor Robert
Bloom, for example, resigned after a
neighbor alleged that he'd repeatedly
shouted the N-word at them. Well, Kent
County Councillor Daniel Taylor was
expelled after being arrested for
threatening to kill his wife. This isn't
even a complete list. There's possibly
worse examples in there. I just had to
stop arbitrarily because otherwise this
video would be mind-numbingly long and
boring. Probably my favorite loss of a
Reform councillor is David Taylor, who
quit the party live on TV in a scene
which I can only describe as bringing
the energy of a reality TV confessional
booth to the Sunday morning BBC Politics
Midlands Show. I mean, I walked in here
today as a Reform County Councillor.
I won't be leaving this studio as a
Reform County Councillor. Taylor had
opted to resign his membership of the
party in protest at attempts by the
Reform-run council of which he was a
part to raise council tax by nearly 9%,
something that they later followed
through with.
Because yeah, Reform haven't only been
plagued with dodgy councilors, they've
also failed at pretty much everything
they've tried to do. In a deeply lame
move following its historic election
gains in 2025, the Central Reform Party
had announced its intention to launch
its very own Do Noc Unit led by Zia
Yusuf, the ex-chairman of the party who
had only just recently re-upped his
membership after briefly resigning
following one of the party's MPs calling
for a ban on the wearing of the burqa.
Doers going in to the county councils
looking at where billions of pounds of
council taxpayers money is being spent.
Reform's Do Unit was a pitiful rip-off
of Elon Musk's Do Unit in the US.
Despite the fact that by this point,
Musk's project had already ended in
failure with his team of teenagers
identifying little in the way of
savings. Who's big boss?
It's me.
>> [laughter]
>> That should be obvious. Reform's Do had
an even harder job made of it. For one,
political power in England is heavily
centralized, meaning that local councils
only have so much agency when it comes
to deciding what to spend money on. On
top of this, local government finances
in England are currently stretched
beyond belief after years of cuts to the
amount of money that they receive from
central government. The result was that
there weren't really any savings to
find. In fact, many councils had already
cut services to the bone and were
nevertheless still teetering on the edge
of bankruptcy. Far from cutting taxes,
every single Reform-led council in the
country chose to raise them. The nearly
9% increase in council tax in
Worcestershire is a standout, but only
just. Eight other Reform-run councils
have similarly raised taxes by 3.8%
or more. Where Reform councilors have
been less shy is in adding expenditure
which benefits them. Reform councilors
in Kent walked back a promised 5% pay
cut to counselors and instead handed
themselves a pay rise. One of George
Finch's first acts in office was to
arrange for counselors to be given
permission to spend 150 grand on
political advisers of the sort normally
reserved for Westminster politicians.
So, yeah, Reform's time running local
councils here in the UK has been nothing
short of a car crash. There's little in
the way of achievements
to boast to voters about Farage gets
pretty touchy. You also pledged or some
of your candidates did to cut council
tax when they were trying to win
elections at local level and that's gone
up. So, how can anyone trust anything
you say?
>> wrong, wrong, wrong. As election day
approaches, Farage has begun to seem
kind of shaken. We'll leave it there.
There's no point. There's no point. Just
write some silly story tomorrow. Have
fun with it.
As has been happening elsewhere in the
world, a far-right which had appeared
unstoppable as an outsider political
move can't quite seem to stick [music]
the transition to power.
This is Giorgia Meloni, the Italian
Prime Minister and leader of the
far-right Brothers of Italy party.
[music]
She's speaking to a scrum of journalists
to make clear her feelings about Donald
Trump's war of words with the Pope in
April 2026.
For Meloni to decide to criticize Trump
quite so unequivocally was quite the
turnaround. She'd previously gone to
great lengths to connect herself to the
Trump project. Before being elected, she
was advised by Steve Bannon. She was a
speaker at CPAC in 2019, 2022, and 2025.
We are fed up of a left that presumes to
lecture us even on what the right should
be, what it should do, how it should
behave, and even how it should define
itself. Last year, she flew all the way
to Mar-a-Lago to meet with Trump in the
lead-up to his second inauguration.
That's all changed. It's not just
Trump's attacks on Pope Leo which have
changed Meloni's tune. Across Europe,
far-right politicians who were once
desperate to present themselves as their
country's equivalent to Donald Trump are
now trying to pretend to have never had
anything to do with [music] him.
Alternative for Deutschland leader Alice
Weidel has told members of her party to
stop flying to the US to meet members of
the MAGA movement so much. Marine Le Pen
called Trump's strikes on Iran erratic
and a mistake. [music] CPAC is due to
come to the UK in July as part of an
international tour, but Nigel Farage has
said that he and the Reform Party will
staying away. Trump, it seems, is no
longer a good mascot for the global
right. Meloni, Weidel, Le Pen, Farage,
and their fellow travelers will all have
watched the cringeducing [music] episode
of JD Vance flying to Budapest to hold a
joint press conference with Viktor Orbán
in early April, only for Orbán to lose
catastrophically.
Even if the reasons for Orbán's
declining support were mostly domestic,
it's clear that an endorsement from the
leader of the free world is no longer
enough to move the needle. [music]
On the other end of the spectrum,
they'll also have been watching along as
Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney has
managed to completely turn around the
fortunes of his country's Liberal Party
precisely by hammering an anti-Trump
message. We are in the process of
building our relationships more deeply
in Europe, uh elsewhere around the
world, so
uh
we'll have a partnership on our terms.
Uh there's a win-win possibility there,
but on our terms, not on their terms.
Some of the most recent souring is a
result of very recent events.
>> [music]
>> America and Israel's war on Iran is as
unpopular in Europe as it is in America.
It's kind of worse on some level. At
least in America, you get to take solace
in the fact that it's your own
government which has decided to press
the make everything more expensive
button for no discernible reason. Folks
elsewhere in the world are facing rising
energy costs and declining living
standards as a result of a war which
they couldn't have less to do with.
[music]
Interestingly, many far-right leaders
instinctively jumped to support Trump
when the strikes on Iran first began.
[music] Farage told Sky News that we
should be supporting the Americans. I
said from day one we should be
supporting the Americans. The vice
president of Le Pen's National Rally
Party reacted similarly. [music]
It was only as the impact began to be
felt in people's wallets that they both
performed an about-face. It's like even
they can sense something of a low hum
vibe shift, a hesitancy.
For the first time since Donald Trump
came down that escalator to announce his
presidential run in 2015, that
inevitable victory of the global right
appears to be hitting some very real
stumbling blocks.
In the name of Oog the Beneficent, the
Merciful, all praise is due to Oog, for
he is Lord of all the worlds.
I want to thank you all for electing me
for MP tonight, and my reign will begin
from today. Broadstairs. Oog Akbar!
This is not a video of Nigel Farage. It
is instead a video of some of his rivals
for the parliamentary seat of [music]
South Thanet during the 2015 general
election. If you're a regular watcher of
my videos, you'll likely have seen it
before in a piece that I made telling
the intertwining tales of Keir Starmer
and Nigel Farage last summer. Fun fact,
my laptop has decided that when I start
typing in the website for Getty Images
to find footage for projects, it should
auto-complete to the URL of this
specific video. We will regularly just
be in the office, and my computer will
just start shouting about Oog the
Beneficent. One of the key takeaways of
that video was that Nigel Farage has
historically been bad at winning
elections, really bad. That piece of
footage was filmed after he'd just
failed at his seventh attempt to become
an MP. It wasn't until 2024
that Nigel Farage actually got into
Parliament, a full 27 years after he
first started trying.
>> [music]
>> The most fascinating thing about Nigel
Farage's career, however, is that this
has never really mattered. In fact,
losing has tended to work extremely well
for our Nige. He's managed to maintain
this presence as a constant specter
haunting British [music] politics in
such a way that both the Conservative
and Labour parties have felt as if they
have had to adopt policies that his
voters would like in order to stave off
his competition. Hence Europhile David
Cameron opting to hold a referendum on
the UK's membership of the European
Union. Let me be clear.
Leaving Europe would threaten our
economic and our national security. Or
former celebrated human rights lawyer
Keir Starmer talking endlessly about
stopping of the boats. It's a good
position to be in and has similarly been
a good position to be in for many
far-right parties. The success of
far-right parties in many countries
across the globe has been in their
ability to act as a lightning rods for
popular discontent with the status quo.
The leaders of these parties have carved
themselves in Trump's image as outsider
candidates ready to tear things up.
Governing, however, is something else
entirely.
We already saw in 2020 that the outrage
which is currently driving people to
vote for norm-defying right-wing
politicians is not unstoppable. The
chaos and incompetency which often
defines their contact with power is
easily overlooked by their most loyal
supporters, but tends to put the softer
supporters that they also need to win
off. Sure, [snorts] for a while it might
be possible to blame the deep state or
the blob or the courts or central
bankers, but after a while those excuses
begin to wear thin. Nigel Farage and the
Reform Party are likely to do very well
in this week's local elections in the
UK. [music]
What that means in the longer term,
however, is far less clear.
Should Reform take a bunch more councils
then end up putting up taxes or
otherwise causing chaos, it could make
Farage's path to a victory [music] at
the national level harder, not easier.
The global far right have until [music]
this point thrived off the chaos of
financial crises, pandemics, and war,
but when the chaos becomes
unattributable to anyone but themselves,
there's every chance that their luck
could run out.
That, however, depends on voters hearing
about these failures. We live in
polarized and polarizing times in which
many of us are consuming entirely
different media diets to one another.
Take Donald Trump's often entirely
self-defeating [music]
use of trade tariffs. Last month, Trump
announced that he was considering
imposing new tariffs on the UK in an
effort to get our government here to
scrap the 2% digital services tax which
it currently levies on big tech firms.
Different newspapers presented this
story in completely different ways. And
if you're someone who, like me, really
values being able to see how stories are
being reported by different media
outlets in this way, then today's video
sponsor Ground News is an incredible
tool. Ground News brings together
reporting from over 50,000 sources
worldwide on any given story. Their app
and website easily shows you the
political leanings of different outlets,
who owns them, and how factual they tend
to be. You can then decide for yourself
how those contextual factors might be
impacting the reporting.
If we use Ground News Story to track
down different takes on the tariff
threats, we can see that 45 different
sources reported on this story. The
left-leaning Daily Mirror emphasized the
size and revenues of the companies which
have to pay this tax in a manner which
kind of suggested that they deserve to
pay it. By contrast, the right-wing
outlet GB News embraced Donald Trump's
framing of the digital services tax as a
cash grab. One of the tools I
particularly like on Ground News is its
blind spot feature, which showcases the
stories each day which one side of the
political aisle are obsessing over while
the other is almost completely ignoring.
When ICE began scaling back some of its
more controversial practices in April,
for example, right-wing outlets largely
ignored the story, perhaps worrying that
it might be seen as evidence that ICE,
and therefore Trump, was failing. But
it's not just me. Ground News has picked
up a bunch of other praise for their
work. The mobile app has been featured
five times as Apple's app of the day,
and the Nobel Peace Center have
celebrated the app as an excellent way
to stay informed, avoid echo chambers,
and expand your worldview.
If you want to get access to all these
great features and adopt a new way of
seeing the news, then I partnered with
them to get you 40% off the same
unlimited access vantage plan that I use
by either scanning the QR code on the
screen or going to my link
ground.news/tomnicholas.
That makes it come out to around £5 a
month, which is a small price to pay for
being able to see how the media is
working to shape narratives at this
really deep level. That link again is
ground.news/tomnicholas.
Thank you so much again to Ground News
for sponsoring today's video and to you
for watching. All that's left for me to
do is say a massive thank you to the
folks who support my work over at the
top tier on my Patreon over at
patreon.com/tomnicholas.
Those people are Richard, Gary, Dick on
Spain, Bill Mitchell, ZC Reese, Zoe
Alden, Alexander Blank, Niels
Zebildgard, Sophia R, Sergio Suarez,
Richard Rapun, Gabriel Coke, Jimmy Dunn,
Fiasco Linguini, Agent Maxwell, Glenn
Sugden, Emil Jaraba, Yunus Emre, Publius
Hedericus, Sam Fortunato, Douglas
Urquhart, and Ahmed Hariche. If you want
to join them in supporting what me and
my team do, or to also getting access to
stuff like my Friday update, in which I
let people know what I'm working on,
often early access to stuff that we're
working on and sneak peeks at stuff, as
well as scripts for the videos, you can
find out how to do so at about
patreon.com/tomnicholas.
Thank you so much for watching once
again, and I'll see you in the next
video.